<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="tanutama.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="tanutama.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-04-29T16:17:11+08:00</updated><id>tanutama.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">+ Albert</title><subtitle>Social Value Design Practitioner. Crafting ideas and possibilities to make positive societal impact. 
</subtitle><author><name>Albert Hardy</name></author><entry><title type="html">PTL Closing Retreat - Part 2</title><link href="tanutama.com/notes/2021/11/ptl-closingretreat2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PTL Closing Retreat - Part 2" /><published>2021-11-06T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-11-06T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>tanutama.com/notes/2021/11/ptl-closingretreat2</id><content type="html" xml:base="tanutama.com/notes/2021/11/ptl-closingretreat2/">&lt;p class=&quot;sublead&quot;&gt;Program Retrospective and Cowtopia Part 2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/11/ptl-tree.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;PTL Trees&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;This is the end of PTL journey and therefore this final retreat is organised around following topics for the group reflecting back our 6+ months journey together:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fishbowl discussion on Psychological Wellbeing for Product Leaders&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharing on Product Tonic Community Journey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experiential learning to create space for difficult conversations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Program retrospective&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;psychological-wellbeing-for-product-leaders&quot;&gt;Psychological Wellbeing for Product Leaders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/11/ptl-chrysalis.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   height=&quot;400px&quot;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;We started this session with the Body Scan exercise with Michelle Ow from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chrysalists.asia/&quot;&gt;Chrysalists&lt;/a&gt; to intentionally notice various parts of our body where we are holding tension for self-awareness, support and relaxation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some key takeaways from this exercise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;noticing your body; physical debt (e.g. lack of sleep) can affect your emotion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When I listen to my body, I become more conscious in how I react to my surroundings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;exercise calmness in the midst of challenging circumstance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reflection-of-product-tonic-in-building-bridges-for-product-leadership-in-southeast-asia&quot;&gt;Reflection of Product Tonic in Building Bridges for Product Leadership in Southeast Asia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We learnt that PTL program is very much inspired by creating awareness and capacity for deeper levels for change and learning from the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Presence-Exploration-Profound-Organizations-Society-ebook/dp/B000FCKBNO&quot;&gt;“Presence: An Exploration of Profound Change in People, Organisations and Society”&lt;/a&gt; described below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Complex, interdependent issues are increasingly shaping the context for strategy. Yet the pressures created by these issues tend to keep leaders in a continual “doing’ mode, with little or no time for reflection and real thinking. We believe that there is a greater need than ever for leaders to meet and genuinely “think together’ — the real meaning of dialogue. Only through creating such opportunities can there be any hope of building the shared understanding and coordinated innovative action”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/11/ptlretreat2-3.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;As we move toward an age of augmented work, there’s a shift from the market economy (with standardized jobs heading toward automation) to the networked economy (with unique, intangible tasks and work that require human skills like curiosity, creativity, empathy, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where lifelong learning through participation in programs like PTL adds value. It helps us move from a structured work team, action based &amp;amp; hierarchical environment into learning together, making sense of knowledge and testing alternatives. Afterwards, to further share knowledge through channels like professional/social networks and gain more diverse perspectives and feedback — i.e. Triple Loop Learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/11/ptlretreat2-4.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;In the course of 6+ months, this is what has happened:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The cohort come from different backgrounds and experiences — i.e. there’s diversity among us (“Professional Social Networks”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Product Tonic Lab (PTL) is the container for us to come together to learn. We seek new knowledge as “Communities of Practice”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To make sense of the knowledge we learn (e.g. on the topics such as trust, resilience, mentorship, ownership, product-led culture, etc), we form Work Teams (i.e. Meetup / Cactus Team) where we can deepen our understanding.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then, the Work Team shares the lesson back to the PTL group. Each meet-up represents an opportunity for each Work Team to design and influence change in the group. And, this allows the group to reflect and identify our own learning edge.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As we wrap up our PTL journey, the expectation is now for us — as a collective and an individual — to share the knowledge back to our own work environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-were-here--what-brings-ptl-community-together&quot;&gt;Why we’re here — What brings PTL community together&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there are many communities of practices and options for learning we can choose from — the motivation and relationship for participation are often transactional in nature i.e. focused on &lt;em&gt;“What can help sharpen my skills”&lt;/em&gt; for young/junior professionals and &lt;em&gt;“What is next for me”&lt;/em&gt; for busy/senior professionals. It makes sustaining a community for long term challenging as both groups will start to drift apart once career/life events happen or members get what they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brought realisation of the importance of creating space for co-creation by bringing societal problems that require dialogue and co-generative actions for both groups to work together and sustain their energy for the learning to truly become meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Product Tonic group was subsequently established with following purpose:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support a safe environment where we can share, ask questions and collaborate on product, team, organisation topics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Forge meaningful relationships in the network and help each other grow in their life and career&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-outcome-that-ptl-community-seek-to-achieve&quot;&gt;The outcome that PTL community seek to achieve&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of making an impact, proceeds from PTL contribute toward providing quality education for the Baan Dada community at the Myanmar border. The hope from this example is that participants of PTL programs would apply our skills &amp;amp; expertise in product and leadership into areas that need dialogue or people don’t pay attention to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, it helps to know how to &lt;strong&gt;create space for difficult conversations&lt;/strong&gt; in topics surrounding wicked problems and sustainable development goals: no poverty, zero hunger, good health and well-being, quality education, gender equality, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/11/ptlretreat2-5.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cowtopia Part 2&lt;/strong&gt; is an example of how we can create such space. During the exercise, we observed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While difficult topics might lead to difficult conversations and confusion…it also encourages us to discover new insights:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the midst of chaos, considerations of feelings &amp;amp; concerns can get brushed aside;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being comfortable with discomfort is necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leader plays a crucial role in the discussion: they set the initial tone, their leadership style and power can influence emotion in the team, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is no such thing as ‘too big to handle’ problem when you have a group of committed people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/11/ptlretreat2-6.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Never doubt that a small group of thoughtful, committed citizens can change the world: indeed, it’s the only thing that ever has.” — Margaret Mead, anthropologist&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;retrospective&quot;&gt;Retrospective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this part, we reflect on significant events over the course of the program/engagement, arriving at a group understanding of lessons learned, and identifying executable action items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gather Data using methods like 6 thinking hats:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;[GOOD] : “Working on this program was good because …”;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;[BAD] : “Working on this program was bad because …”;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;[BETTER] : “Working on this program could have been better if …”;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;[BEST] : “Working on this program gave us a chance to do some of our best work, such as …”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generate Insight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decide What to Do&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some notable key feedback from PTL Cohort 1 Program:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;good--things-that-work-well&quot;&gt;[GOOD — Things that work well]&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Opportunity to learn with one another — Hearing others stories, perspective and growth from different experiences, region, cultures and even language&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go out of comfort zone, practice things that I don’t really do much&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enhance confidence level to discuss virtually with other leader across the region&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Space to reflect (on my trajectory, my output/outcome to my environment; value, purpose, life, meaning) and distill learnings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have longer time to interact, get to know and build relationship &amp;amp; trust as cohort&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experimenting with different ways to have dialogue — fishbowl, circle way, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Great opportunity to struggle together during meetups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bad--things-that-pose-challenges&quot;&gt;[BAD — Things that pose challenges]&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Challenge to track milestones or learning progress; Confusing at the start but got better over time — Learning style was challenging and took some getting used to, especially if coming into the session with the expectation having “structured” sessions on topics we wanted to learn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prompts/topics are mentally taxing at times — necessary conversations that I wish I could have prepared (in advance) for better (dialogue)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Self leading — meaning you rely on yourself to get all of the information needed. Putting in more time for digesting all the input and reflecting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time and long commitment period — Taking much more energy that expected to see through the program&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;best--valuable-takeaways&quot;&gt;[BEST — Valuable takeaways]&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eye-opener and gaining new perspective on various topics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meet new people, learn new ways and tools to facilitate. Get to see in person how everyone else is lost/confused and just doing whatever they can&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being empowered with tools to teach without being a deemed EXPERT in it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learning self and others thru fun engaging facilitation — Becoming more aware about self&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New methods of facilitation and learning how to facilitate better&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Practice) Commitment, self-discipline, resilience, persistence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using principles of product management outside of “product management work” — in self, in orgs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making connections with product peers &amp;amp; mentors over prolonged period&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strong team work for meetup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;concluding-notes&quot;&gt;Concluding Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PTL has been enriching journey of discovery — Expect lots of efforts, commitment, and resilience to pull it through. It is not a program for learning instant product skills. Instead, PTL offers safe space for participants to experience, experiment and nurture deep collaboration and meaningful dialogue. Participants well being, coaching and support by PTL Facilitors (Michael, Mul and Ignas) have been fantastic!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the program, there are many awesome creativity, surprises and laughters from meetup workshops organised by all cactus teams (Note: The bar is getting higher for each subsequent meetup!). It is inspiring to experience care and commitment from each teams in preparing materials to bring the most relevant learning experience for the cohort. A big appreciation especially to my cactus team member (Y and R) who embrace the challenge and journey through many nights and weekends of preparations. Looking back, those are moments that I cherished the most!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, this is the program that provide you with a mentor that you can reach out and talk to. I didn’t mention much in this aspect of PTL mentorship here — but it is one of the most valuable you could ever gain from this program. I was fortunate to be able to connect and have deep conversations some of the mentors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drop me a note or reach out to Michael Ong if you’re interested to find out more and see if this is the right program for you. I’m glad I did!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Albert Hardy</name></author><category term="workshop" /><summary type="html">Program Retrospective and Cowtopia Part 2</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PTL Closing Retreat - Part 1</title><link href="tanutama.com/notes/2021/10/ptl-closingretreat1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PTL Closing Retreat - Part 1" /><published>2021-10-24T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-10-24T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>tanutama.com/notes/2021/10/ptl-closingretreat1</id><content type="html" xml:base="tanutama.com/notes/2021/10/ptl-closingretreat1/">&lt;p class=&quot;sublead&quot;&gt;Knowing your Self in Leadership&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlretreat1-1.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;The closing retreat is designed to close off learning backlog items uncovered from previous meetup 10 (Inviting Leadership in Yourself) and expand our self-awareness using the Johari Window model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understanding the leadership concept in general&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase the awareness of one’s leadership power and style by getting feedback from our own Cactus (i.e. Meetup) Team&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase the awareness of one’s self leadership, specifically power and style&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sunday-mindful-yoga-with-teresa-thuy-pham&quot;&gt;Sunday Mindful Yoga with Teresa Thuy Pham&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is said that: “When you can control the body, you can control the mind.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started with Sunday Mindful Yoga with Teresa Thuy — a series of yoga movements designed to explore, establish, and bolster our mind and body connection awareness. Reflecting back, following articles helps me better understand about the purpose and benefit of the activity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mindfulness is a way of training yourself to simply focus on whatever is happening in the present moment…with Mindful Yoga, the main focus is on mind-body awareness, as opposed to alignment details and the exact physical posture… (It) places great importance on observing your mind and feelings while you are acting out the yoga pose - &lt;a href=&quot;https://positivepsychology.com/mindfulness-yoga/&quot;&gt;Ref&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Positioning your body in certain ways can have immediate effects on your mental and emotional state. Being aware of your body language and what it reveals about your attitudes and feelings can help you to change your attitudes and feelings just by changing your physical posture - &lt;a href=&quot;https://palousemindfulness.com/docs/yoga.pdf&quot;&gt;Ref&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The body senses rather than thinks…The body scan teaches us how to lean gently into discomfort… (which) reduces the unwelcome sensations’ power to derail us. By paying attention to body sensations, and noticing what arises in awareness, we incline our interest into being alive, not as a set of philosophical ideas, but as actual phenomena — the very experience of things. This enables us to tune into the actuality of moment-by-moment living, generating appreciation that can nurture a sense of awe and gratitude - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mindful.org/7-qualities-mindfulness-trained-body-scan/&quot;&gt;Ref&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;knowing-your-self-in-leadership-with-mulyadi--ignatius&quot;&gt;Knowing your Self in Leadership with Mulyadi &amp;amp; Ignatius&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In “Where do you see yourself in self-leadership”, we re-visited concepts introduced in the opening retreats and identified leadership concepts that resonate with us the most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlretreat1-2.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;There are quite diverse definitions that resonate with the cohort:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Leadership is the collective action of everyone you influence. Your behavior — your actions and your words — determines how you influence. Our job as leaders is to energize whatever marshals action within others.” — &lt;strong&gt;David Caullo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Leadership is not a person or a position. It is a complex moral relationship between people, based on trust, obligation, commitment, emotion, and a shared vision of the good.” — &lt;strong&gt;Joanne Ciulla&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Leadership is an opportunity to serve. It is not a trumpet call to self-importance.” — &lt;strong&gt;J. Donald Walters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Leadership is solving problems. The day soldiers stop bringing you their problems is the day you have stopped leading them. They have either lost confidence that you can help or concluded you do not care. Either case is a failure of leadership.” — Colin Powell&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Leadership is doing what is right when no one is watching.” — &lt;strong&gt;George Van Valkenburg&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A man who can persuade people to do what they don’t want to do, or do what they’re too lazy to do, and like it.” — &lt;strong&gt;Harry S. Truman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group noted Leadership is not just about making right decisions but also about enablement — creating safe space for others to make decisions. As one participant put it : &lt;em&gt;“leadership as an effect, and causing a ripple effect in everyone you influence, be it good or bad”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aspect-of-leadership-practice&quot;&gt;Aspect of Leadership Practice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During PTL we explored 2 practice of Leadership: Shared Leadership and Rotating Leadership&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shared-leadership&quot;&gt;Shared Leadership&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlretreat1-3.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;In this “Shared Leadership” model, the formal leadership role remains usually with one person in charge (e.g. the manager or team lead). Members are empowered to actively take actions to remove obstacles or seek opportunities. Shared leadership allows us to learn and complement each other.
The group shared stories around constraints of time, ideas, doubts and moving from consensus to consent, making things fun and taking little steps to achieve each meetup. Some tips / lesson learned from how did the cohort practice shared leadership — their decision making process and challenges when designing and/or delivering the meetup:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open communication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Celebrate small victories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Democratic; recognise each other’s strength&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Common time — schedule ahead (responsibility to make meetup work)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rotating-leadership&quot;&gt;Rotating Leadership&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlretreat1-4.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;“Rotating Leadership” is one of 3 principles of “Circle Way” (i.e. technique PTL practiced to enable intentional and safe space for group interactions). Here, the formal leadership role rotates among the members, alternating decision control between partners to access their complementary capabilities. This allows team members to become leaders and experiment with new things and pick up new skills on the go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rotating leadership is being practiced through meetups organised by the “PTL Cactus team”. Each cactus team leads the cohort in exploring topics across &lt;em&gt;Product Leadership / Decisions / Trust / Sustainability / Resilience / Mentorship / Ownership / Culture / Economy / Self&lt;/em&gt; providing an opportunity to design/influence change in the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some observations from practicing “rotating leadership”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can learn by observing and following — Allowing others to lead creates learning opportunities about how other people do it, their points of view and their styles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deepen and broaden team’s knowledge through different perspectives while reducing blind spot&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Uncovering complementary strength of everyone in the team.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trust people to lead and give everyone opportunities to lead so they grow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Great to empower and delegate, so that everyone can build new skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;leadership-power-and-styles&quot;&gt;Leadership Power and Styles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlretreat1-5.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Leadership Power and Styles&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;Having completed the journey of leading and organising meetups as team, we revisit understanding of ourselves in :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leadership Power&lt;/strong&gt; : Coercive, Reward, Legitimate, Expert, Referent, Information, Charismatic, Moral and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leadership Style&lt;/strong&gt; : Authoritarian, Participative, Delegative, Transactional, Transformational. Servant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Power&lt;/strong&gt; = a person’s ability to control activities of other individuals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlretreat1-6.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Leadership Power&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Style&lt;/strong&gt; = frameworks developed that describe main ways that people lead&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlretreat1-7.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Leadership Styles&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;We are invited in exercise to gather and compare our self-assessment with feedback from our peers — i.e. to see whether there’s a gap between how we see our leadership style and power and how others see it and help each other to deepen their understanding of their own leadership style and power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each cactus team is requested to reflect following question: &lt;em&gt;How would you assess your own and your team members’ leadership style and power as meetup facilitators (when designing or delivering meetup)?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlretreat1-8.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Johari Windows&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;Here we are using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fearlessculture.design/blog-posts/the-johari-window&quot;&gt;“Johari Window”&lt;/a&gt; as psychological tool of soliciting, conveying and accepting feedback. With the help of such feedback, we can gain awareness of our positive and negative traits as perceived by others and better recognise issues that may inhibit team dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this exercise enriching and meaningful as it was given by fellow peers who has been journeying closely throughout PTL. Through the dialogue and sharing, we give and receive affirmation of our strengths and open up new work areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following quote by Lao Tzu gave timely reminder and inspiration for role of leadership regardless of their preferred choice of power and styles, i.e. &lt;em&gt;ability to encourage and inspire outstanding work in the team without taking any credit for themselves — finding pure satisfaction in the accomplishment of others.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlretreat1-9.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Lao Tzu Approach to Leadership&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-invitation-for-yourself&quot;&gt;What is the invitation for yourself?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wrap up this Closing Retreat by spending time drawing together to conceptualise and declare leadership areas we aim to work on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Step 1 — Draw a timeline / landscape of last 5 months&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Use symbols e.g. Circle = Wholeness, Rectangle = Support, Triangle = Goal, Spiral = Change, Star person = wholeness&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Step 2 — Zoom into a specific area&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Draw deeper into what is emerging and add details&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Step 3 — Looking at symbols that represent possibilities (e.g. Risk, Investment, Seed, Goals, Flow) and Think about your next step&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;What is the invitation you can draw and declare (assert) for yourself to work on yourself in Leadership?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlretreat1-10.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;h3 id=&quot;side-quest&quot;&gt;Side Quest&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://maraineyassociates.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/Leading-in-a-Learning-Way.pdf&quot;&gt;Leading in a Learning Way&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/decentralized-decision-making-service-what-daniel-mezick/&quot;&gt;Decentralized Decision-Making: In Service to What?&lt;/a&gt;
-&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.managementstudyhq.com/types-of-leadership-power.html&quot;&gt;What is Leadership Power? Types of Leadership Power&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://yscouts.com/blog/types-of-leadership-power/&quot;&gt;8 Types of Power for Today’s Leaders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rapidstartleadership.com/5-great-ways-to-get-information-power-working-for-you/&quot;&gt;5 Ways to get Information Power Working for You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Albert Hardy</name></author><category term="workshop" /><summary type="html">Knowing your Self in Leadership</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Conversations &amp;amp; Notes from 4th Product Tonic Unconference 2021</title><link href="tanutama.com/notes/2021/10/ptl-4th-unconference/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Conversations &amp;amp; Notes from 4th Product Tonic Unconference 2021" /><published>2021-10-23T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-10-23T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>tanutama.com/notes/2021/10/ptl-4th-unconference</id><content type="html" xml:base="tanutama.com/notes/2021/10/ptl-4th-unconference/">&lt;p class=&quot;sublead&quot;&gt;Building Bridges for Product Leadership in Southeast Asia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlunconference-1.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;Being participants of Product Tonic Lab, we’re exposed to various approaches to establish dialogue and collaboration from within small groups using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thecircleway.net/&quot;&gt;The Circle Way&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theworldcafe.com/&quot;&gt;The World Cafe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fishbowl_(conversation)&quot;&gt;Fishbowl Conversation&lt;/a&gt; to the large group through this Product Tonic Unconference, which is based on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_Space_Technology&quot;&gt;Open Space Technology method&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This by far is the most participative and engaging virtual dialogue session and environment I’ve attended — no mean feat given engagement and interaction have been the largest challenge when it comes to virtual events. Plus, without the usual awkwardness that infiltrates breakout sessions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introductions-and-check-in-to-unconference-space&quot;&gt;Introductions and Check-In to Unconference space&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who are new to Open Space &amp;amp; Unconference concept:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-unconference&quot;&gt;What is Unconference?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unconference#:~:text=An%20unconference%20is%20a%20participant,presentations%20and%20top%2Ddown%20organization.&quot;&gt;unconference&lt;/a&gt; is a participant driven meeting with high level structure to provide a clear sense of purpose but without predefined topics to create an informal and open atmosphere. The actual topics are generated on the spot by the participants based on the overall theme proposed by the organizer while breakout discussion groups are formed dynamically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-unconference&quot;&gt;Why Unconference?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Less up-front planning. Organiser does not need to set up a detailed agenda ahead of time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greater flexibility. The issues that are most important to people will be raised, attended and discussed by the participants best capable of getting something done about them. Participants co-create the agenda and may discover unexpected topics that are of relevance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spontaneous conversations and higher energy levels. The open space format encourages informal conversations to get to know each other, exchange knowledge, and build trust. Participants will likely feel engaged and energized by the process given the focus on issues that matter to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple rules to remember when attending the Unconference (known as Open Space Principles):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whoever comes is the right people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whenever it starts is the right time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whatever happens is the only thing that could have&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When it’s over, it’s over&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wherever it happens is the right place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlunconference-2.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Open Space Principles&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;Above principles are also complemented with the &lt;strong&gt;“Law of Mobility”&lt;/strong&gt; : &lt;em&gt;If at any time during our time together you find yourself in any situation where you are neither learning nor contributing, go someplace else&lt;/em&gt;. This means all participants are given both the right and the responsibility to maximize their own learning and contribution, which the Law assumes only participants themselves can ultimately judge and control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-theme&quot;&gt;The Theme&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guiding theme for this 4th Product Tonic Unconference held on Saturday 23rd Oct is &lt;strong&gt;“Building Bridges for Product Leadership in Southeast Asia”&lt;/strong&gt; which is about exploring how we can create a space for co-creation to bridge young/junior professionals, busy/senior professionals and what needs dialogue and co-generative action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Unconference agenda is structured as following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10:00 Introductions and Check-In to Unconference space&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10:15 User Experience Fishbowl with Product Leaders in Southeast Asia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;11:05 Mindful Movement with Teresa Thuy Pham&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;11:20 to 14:00 Open Space Begins&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14:00 to 14:30 Unconference Closing and Check-Out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A total of 108 participants signed up with 58 participants coming from Southeast Asia communities of practice for product people. Besides enriching conversation around Product Leadership / Decisions / Trust / Sustainability / Resilience / Mentorship / Ownership / Culture / Economy / Self — The Unconference also making a difference by donating the proceeds towards providing for university education for the children from &lt;a href=&quot;https://baandada.net/&quot;&gt;Baan Dada&lt;/a&gt; — a safe home for disadvantaged children situated on the border of Thailand and Myanmar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;user-experience-fishbowl-conversations-with-product-leaders-in-southeast-asia&quot;&gt;User Experience Fishbowl Conversations with Product Leaders in Southeast Asia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a facilitated conversation with Sander Veraar, Jeremy Ong, Tomas Li, Huishan Lim, Mike Dickinson who have contributed their time and energy over the years, nurturing conversations in the Southeast Asia product space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlunconference-3.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;The Unconference notes is shared according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chatham_House_Rule&quot;&gt;Chatham House Rule&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check In — What words would you use to describe where your head is? And where your heart is?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collective exuberance, at ease…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self — Over the past year, how have you taken care of yourself?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spending time with family and create time for self-reflect&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being appreciative that we’re in a place that is relatively safe. Do more exercise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adjusting to a new normal — learning mindfulness; checking in “inside” since can’t travel outside; creating more opportunities for learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deliberately minimise screen time and virtual meets; commit to some major personal decisions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop awareness of things to be grateful of and being kind to yourself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Culture — What do you think of this statement “Culture is the interactions and relations between people”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We were not born with culture — We were imposed and immersed in it which shaped who we are. Still, culture can also be a choice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Culture is a common belief as a group of people in organisations and society — what you prefer &amp;amp; not to prefer. There’s always something new to discover and relearn.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Culture is like “the water that the fish lives in” — you don’t really see and feel but it governs &amp;amp; influences everything. Interactions and relations between people will happen within this environment along with our own individual agency as to how we choose to interact with it. Whatever you do will have ripple effect&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Culture is permeating — you as an individual have the choice to help determine the ripples. The influence can come from within yourself or imposed by the world if you decide not to do anything about it. You don’t have to wait to be given (hierarchical) leadership to make and influence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who defines the culture?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While top-down company culture can happen (wanted by upper management) — In reality, it is not what they say but what they do.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Culture can come from bravery of people who are proud of who they are, self-confident in what they do, have the belief and take action. It is about the behavior of the individuals around you. Individuals can create team cultures, expand into organisation cultures and eventually company culture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We often underestimate our ability to define the culture. We can have a huge influence and impact on culture (particularly in teams and family) given our willingness to engage &amp;amp; lead by example.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One important conversation to have is to establish explicit agreement about what the group culture should be. This will help minimise misunderstanding and frustration in doing what different members consider “right”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find ways to codify the culture so that it is not so fragile — cognition may change as people change.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Culture is the sum and accumulation of spoken and unspoken language around values which doesn’t change much in organisation. Example, transparency as values will remain, but the act of respecting transparency may change as organisation grows. In other words, Culture always changes because people change but the values might stay the same.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Values like destination, as you walk toward the destination, all the things you did and talk about becomes your culture with working agreement can be the “umbrella” to overcome challenges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decisions — What is a significant decision you have made in the last year? How has it impacted you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Speaking out, giving yourself permission to create your own personal space and not to feel guilty about it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resilience — What is something you came across recently that gave you hope or inspiration?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wrote a book to codify organisation core values and stories to share with new hires&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People starts care more about social issues and welfare of others — there’s a lot more boldness and energy to harness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check Out — What is your answer to life, universe and everything at this time in your life?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;42 (The unconf is held week 42 of 2021!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We’re the universe’s self conscious — without us, the universe does not know it exists. Learning and understanding how the world works is just the universe trying to understand itself. Education is the number one most important thing; without it the universe will not know itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mindful-movement-with-teresa-thuy-pham&quot;&gt;Mindful Movement with Teresa Thuy Pham&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlunconference-4.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Mindfulness Exercise with a Cup of Tea&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;Teresa guided participants to build moments of mindfulness into the day to connect our mind and body through simple exercise of enjoying a cup of tea with our five senses. Highly recommended!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-space-sessions&quot;&gt;Open Space Sessions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlunconference-5.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Open Space Topic Proposal Board&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;8 topics were launched:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/product-team-tonic/what-do-some-of-the-best-product-leaders-youve-worked-with-look-like-8e4732679d3a&quot;&gt;What do some of the best product leaders you’ve worked with look like?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/product-team-tonic/how-do-you-recharge-take-care-of-yourself-as-you-hold-space-for-your-team-and-move-them-2a1e4f3b0f3c&quot;&gt;How do you recharge/take care of yourself as you hold space for your team and move them?&lt;/a&gt; (notes by Kiat Lim)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/product-team-tonic/designing-your-product-leadership-journey-a16ebe0a93ca&quot;&gt;Designing your Product leadership journey&lt;/a&gt; (notes by Michael Ong)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@alberthardy/one-wo-man-band-how-to-handle-being-the-companys-first-pm-811f4f2cf72d&quot;&gt;One-(Wo)Man Band 🥁: How to handle being the company’s first PM?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to communicate the value/contribution of product management to the organisation?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to move from launching features to driving outcomes?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First 90 days in a company&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For various sustainability, how can product leads transform charity model to social businesses (financial, impact, economic)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;closing-and-check-out&quot;&gt;Closing and Check-Out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When it’s over, it’s over — we did a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gallery_walk&quot;&gt;gallery walk&lt;/a&gt; and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reflect on our time together&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plan future actions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be safe as we exit the space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes-on-virtual-unconference-experience&quot;&gt;Notes on Virtual Unconference Experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As reported in The Economist and study by Stanford Univ — a year since the pandemic, many already are suffering from ‘Zoom fatigue’ with the amount of virtual meeting, events and webinars organized and with the way the technology is designed: randomly arranged grids, awkward silences, endless eye contact, lack of social and non-verbal cues to build trust, and more.
There have been efforts to recreate in-person events experiences and interactions online more bearable, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.geekwire.com/2020/will-meeting-suck-less-virtual-auditorium-microsoft-unveils-new-together-mode-teams/&quot;&gt;Microsoft Teams “Together Mode”&lt;/a&gt; which removes visual distractions and places participants as if they are in the same room to make meetings feel more natural and help participants focus on non-verbal cues.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vulcanpost.com/750578/gather-town-review-virtual-meeting-tools-workplace-collaboration/&quot;&gt;Gather Town&lt;/a&gt;, which is sort of a cross between Zoom and 8-bit retro video games with the ability to move around and interact with other participants based on your avatar’s locations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Upcoming &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oculus.com/blog/workrooms/&quot;&gt;Meta’s Horizon Workrooms&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2021/11/2/22758974/microsoft-teams-metaverse-mesh-3d-avatars-meetings-features&quot;&gt;Microsoft Metaverse Mesh&lt;/a&gt; which bring VR-based immersive meeting space with expressive avatars for sense of presence and physical gestures using hands for more natural interactions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, the one I’m excited the most comes through the way this Unconference is designed and run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptlunconference-6.png&quot;  alt=&quot;&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Product Tonic Unconference on Welo.Space&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;This year, the organiser chose to experiment using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.welo.space/&quot;&gt;Welo Space&lt;/a&gt; — a relatively new player with great potential. I’m impressed with how well thought-out features provided:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beautifully designed 3D spaces providing clear cues of sessions buzzing with activity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Background Blur Camera mitigating privacy concerns for turning on camera&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seamless integration with collaboration apps like Google Docs and Miro (a real time online whiteboard) therefore less tinkering &amp;amp; context switch with multiple windows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3D environments may first appear as gimmicky (nice to see but no real value) — however I began to appreciate how such environment can really help with spatial cues for effective social interaction. It becomes clearer to signal intention to participate by moving in and out from the circle and easier to notice such subtle cue as compare to raised hand emoji. Their space designs could help participants feel different vibes (e.g. formal, informal) and sense of connections to surrounding others. I’m also glad there’s no awkward keyboard to navigate around — simply double click to teleport across rooms. You can also have the choice for a quiet retreat space to focus without distractions while still staying present. This is the kind of solution that I found deliver more effective human connection in a Hybrid Digital Workplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the Unconference shows how impactful the dialogue could be with the right combination of facilitation skills, technology platform and participants.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Albert Hardy</name></author><category term="workshop" /><summary type="html">Building Bridges for Product Leadership in Southeast Asia</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PTL #10 - Self</title><link href="tanutama.com/notes/2021/10/ptl-meetup10/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PTL #10 - Self" /><published>2021-10-07T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-10-07T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>tanutama.com/notes/2021/10/ptl-meetup10</id><content type="html" xml:base="tanutama.com/notes/2021/10/ptl-meetup10/">&lt;p class=&quot;sublead&quot;&gt;“How might we increase self-awareness and understand leadership style?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facilitated by Mic, Mul and Nas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we learnt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experiential Learning Cycle and RSVP Fundamentals of Leadership&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Revisiting on Product Person Canvas and journal for increasing self-awareness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;experiential-learning-cycle-and-rsvp-model-leadership&quot;&gt;Experiential Learning Cycle and RSVP Model Leadership&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One the most important challenge in leadership today is to develop competence in adjusting to a radically altered environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptl10-2c.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Leading in Learning Way&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;strong&gt;RSVP Model&lt;/strong&gt;, there area four key leadership functions required:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;relationship mastery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strategy mastery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;vision mastery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;performance mastery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central to achieve such proficiency is the ability to deliberately learn from experience. The &lt;strong&gt;Experiential Learning Theory (ELT)&lt;/strong&gt; by Kolb (1984) provides lens to integrate feeling, perceiving, thinking, and doing for effective experiential learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptl10-2a.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Leading in Learning Way&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;In ELT, the experiential learning space is defined by the attracting and repelling forces of experiencing-thinking and reflecting-doing. Learning proceeds as a recursive cycle and results from the integration of four learning modes: concrete experience, reflective observation, abstract conceptualization, and active experimentation. This basic concepts of learning cycle, learning styles, learning space, learning skills described in ELT can be used for training, coaching, team and leadership development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;constellation&quot;&gt;Constellation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cohort also reflected various dimensions of product leadership (Decisions, Trust, Sustainability, Resilience, Mentorship, Ownership, etc) explored in the past 5 months. We found Top 3 key topics that our cohort understood the most are: Relationship building (5 votes), Facilitating conversation (4) and Leadership (4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then explored 2 approaches to help further understanding of those topics and apply them in our work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What can you do to help yourself?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is self-work that’s within our control. Product Person Canvas and the learning backlog can be our compass to identify which topics we need to put more focus on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptl10-3.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Product Person Canvas&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptl10-4.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Learning Backlog&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What can others do to help you?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
When self-work is taken care of, then we can turn to others. Appreciative interview is the manifestation of this — we ask others to help identify the AHAs for us and reduces our blindspot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptl10-5.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Appreciative Interview&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sailboat&quot;&gt;Sailboat&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, the group recap and shared key learning points about product leadership&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/10/ptl10-6.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attribute of Success being a Product Leader&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Curiosity, Honesty&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mental resilience, EQ, Empathy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Facilitative and Listening skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goal and “Knowing when to let go”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenge of being a Product Leader&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Courage to take ownership (difficult conversations)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ego - Being at peace with things you can’t control, Letting go&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;KPI Pressure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;side-quest&quot;&gt;Side Quest&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://maraineyassociates.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/Leading-in-a-Learning-Way.pdf&quot;&gt;Leading in a Learning Way&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Albert Hardy</name></author><category term="workshop" /><summary type="html">“How might we increase self-awareness and understand leadership style?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PTL #9 - Economy</title><link href="tanutama.com/notes/2021/09/ptl-meetup9/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PTL #9 - Economy" /><published>2021-09-09T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-09-09T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>tanutama.com/notes/2021/09/ptl-meetup9</id><content type="html" xml:base="tanutama.com/notes/2021/09/ptl-meetup9/">&lt;p class=&quot;sublead&quot;&gt;“How might we use product skillset in pushing economies into the green circle of the doughnut economy?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/09/ptl9-1b.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Doughnut!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;Facilitated by Steven, Colette, Dominic&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we learnt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understanding doughnut economics and current challenges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having a more sustainable mindset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-doughnut-theory&quot;&gt;The Doughnut Theory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/09/ptl9-1.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Doughnut Theory&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;The Doughnut theory offers a vision of what it means for humanity to thrive in the 21st century. Three things about the Doughnut:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contains social and ecological topics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goal is to live in the green zone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seven ways to think differently:
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Changing the Goal&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;See the big picture&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Nurture human nature&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Get savvy with systems&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Design to distribute&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Create to regenerate&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Be agnostic about growth&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;moving-from-linear-to-circular-economy&quot;&gt;Moving from linear to circular economy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ecological degradation is the result of degenerative industrial process. The economy needs to move from a linear to a circular system and work within the cycle of the living world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/09/ptl9-3.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The caterpillar economy of degenerative industrial design vs. the butterfly economy, regenerative by nature.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sustainable Design Strategies&lt;/strong&gt; examples :&lt;br /&gt;
Modularity, Product Service Systems Models, Longevity, Remanufacture, Recyclability, Repairability, Reusability, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/09/ptl9-4.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Sustainable Design Strategies&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emerging questions&lt;/strong&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HMW shift our mindset to reuse than consume new things?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HMW create infrastructure and incentives around it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how we want to incentivized user to be proactively reuse/recycle their goods&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A lot of consumer product business models rely on continuous consumption — HMW change this “thinking” to incentivize businesses to create longer lasting, more BIFL (buy-it-for-life) products?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/09/ptl9-0.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Group Photo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;h3 id=&quot;side-quest&quot;&gt;Side Quest&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sdgs.un.org/goals&quot;&gt;17 sustainable goals by UN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.designlife-cycle.com/&quot;&gt;Lifecycle of various products&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://circularclassroom.com&quot;&gt;Circular Classroom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5930093/amsterdam-doughnut-economics/&quot;&gt;Case Study of Amsterdam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doughnuteconomics.org/&quot;&gt;Doughnut Economics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://humanjourney.us/the-changing-world-economy-section/doughnut-economics/&quot;&gt;Doughnut Economics Book Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/disruptive-design/quick-guide-to-sustainable-design-strategies-641765a86fb8&quot;&gt;Sustainable Design Strategies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Albert Hardy</name></author><category term="workshop" /><summary type="html">“How might we use product skillset in pushing economies into the green circle of the doughnut economy?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PTL #8 - Culture</title><link href="tanutama.com/notes/2021/08/ptl-meetup8/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PTL #8 - Culture" /><published>2021-08-26T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-08-26T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>tanutama.com/notes/2021/08/ptl-meetup8</id><content type="html" xml:base="tanutama.com/notes/2021/08/ptl-meetup8/">&lt;p class=&quot;sublead&quot;&gt;“How might we influence a &quot;Product Led&quot; culture?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/08/ptl8-0.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Meetup Circle&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;Facilitated by Hafiz, Bennet, Abhijit&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we learnt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Concepts of product led growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn about product led from experience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apply product led concept&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;product-led-growth&quot;&gt;Product-led growth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/08/ptl8-1.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;PLG&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product-led growth (PLG)&lt;/strong&gt; is an end user-focused growth model that relies on the product itself as the primary driver of customer acquisition, conversion, and expansion. 
This can result in a stronger growth engine, lower customer acquisition cost and higher Revenue Per Employee (RPE).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-pillars-of-plg&quot;&gt;3 Pillars of PLG&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design for the  End User&lt;/strong&gt; : putting the needs of real people first, listening to their problems—and committing to make consistent improvements to your product to solve those problems more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Listen to the user&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build a culture of continuous, rapid improvement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Personalize where possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliver Value Before Capturing Value&lt;/strong&gt;  : reduce all potential barriers to users solving an immediate problem&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put the product first&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deliver value quickly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduce customer success before sales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Invest in the Product with Go-to-Market Intent&lt;/strong&gt;  :  drive acquisition, conversion, and expansion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invest in product data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build a growth team&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run experiments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;traditional-companies-vs-product-led-growth&quot;&gt;Traditional Companies vs Product-led growth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Product-led growth impacts company’s go-to-market strategy by placing the product at the helm as compared to traditional organizational structure where profit and cost centre operates separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/08/ptl8-4.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   height=&quot;320px&quot;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Traditional Companies vs Product-led Orgs Comparison &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;Like other go-to-market strategies, product-led growth is a company-wide action plan that informs how sales, marketing, CS, engineering, and product teams measure success and contribute to growth:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sales/marketing led metrics 🠒 Product led metrics e.g. Acquisition, Activation, Retention, Referral &amp;amp; Revenue (AARRR)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Top down driven 🠒 Product working together with business stakeholders to drive value&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on solutions 🠒 Focus on user problems by relying on data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many nuanced blockers that stops a company from being product-led. Some blockers are explicit, but most of them are nuanced - such as (lack of) transparency of information by C-level, (incomplete) structural changes made by the company even with best intentions, and how individuals are onboarded and what’re mantras they’ve been fed early on in their employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Product-led is not the only solution. Companies can be sales-led, marketing-led, customer-led, and much more - there may be more optimal fits based on the industry and structure of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;leading-change&quot;&gt;Leading Change&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bringing change in organization is possible through iterative lean approach and continuous improvements to establish trust among stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/08/ptl8-3.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Lean Change Canvas&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;Reference: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.plays-in-business.com/lean-change-canvas-how-to-deliver-change-best/&quot;&gt;Plays in Business&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;insight-from-the-exercise&quot;&gt;Insight from the exercise:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharing of goals (KPIs/OKRs), information and data can help shift individuals from working on just their own goals, to striving for a more holistic, user-centric approach.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s entirely possible for the decision maker (i.e. the CEO, CPO, etc) not to have all the details and necessary information. Thus, this is an opportunity for everyone else to influence the decision maker by data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One approach in designing a team is by involving the team member. We can invite them to participate and determine which role suits them best. As was seen in the exercise, this involvement in team design led to a high participation rate among all members.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The exercise also highlighted how a leader manages his/her team. Some leaders might be more comfortable using delegative leadership style, i.e. the team members have a freedom of choice on how to get the job done, while others prefer to balance between delegative and authoritarian, to keep the team members in check. The leadership style often plays a role in determining what (or how good) the outcome will be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;side-quest&quot;&gt;Side Quest&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://openviewpartners.com/product-led-growth/&quot;&gt;Product-led growth , explained&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://openviewpartners.com/blog/product-led-companies-why-and-how-they-work/&quot;&gt;Product-led companies: why and how they work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://svpg.com/does-company-culture-matter/&quot;&gt;Does company culture matter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://corporate-rebels.com/reinvent-your-organizational-culture/&quot;&gt;Reinvent your organisational culture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://svpg.com/establishing-a-true-product-culture/&quot;&gt;Establishing true product culture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://svpg.com/product-leadership-is-hard/&quot;&gt;Product leadership is hard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://svpg.com/product-vs-it-mindset/&quot;&gt;Product vs IT mindset&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://svpg.com/product-vs-project-teams/&quot;&gt;Product vs Project teams&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://futureofsaas.io/product-led-vs-sales-led-vs-marketing-led-vs-customer-led-differences/&quot;&gt;Differences of product, sales, marketing and customer-led growth strategy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Albert Hardy</name></author><category term="workshop" /><summary type="html">“How might we influence a &quot;Product Led&quot; culture?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PTL #7 - Ownership</title><link href="tanutama.com/notes/2021/08/ptl-meetup7/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PTL #7 - Ownership" /><published>2021-08-12T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-08-12T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>tanutama.com/notes/2021/08/ptl-meetup7</id><content type="html" xml:base="tanutama.com/notes/2021/08/ptl-meetup7/">&lt;p class=&quot;sublead&quot;&gt;“How might we build a sense of ownership to create success together?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/08/ptl7-2b.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Meetup Circle&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;Facilitated by Albert, Rebecca, Ysabelle&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we learnt and shared:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building a sense of ownership starts with invitations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Game of Ownership (Shark Tank)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recognising stages of team development to identify blockers and the right resolutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;building-a-sense-of-ownership-starts-with-invitations&quot;&gt;Building a sense of ownership starts with invitations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Invitation can test willingness &amp;amp; “pull” people to make choices instead of delegating / “pushing” action or responsibilities onto them. By offering choices (including free will to opt-in / out), we demonstrate respect and likely attract motivated people, increase engagement, strengthen trust and relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-game-of-ownership&quot;&gt;The Game of Ownership&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We played a game constructed to see how leadership, invitation and ownership could play out in the team. The game was loosely inspired by the TV Show “Shark Tank” about entrepreneurs making business presentations to a panel of investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/08/ptl7-1.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Shark Tank&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;2 teams were deliberately setup: one with an “ideal” situation of a supportive Product Owner, motivated interns and has unlimited resources, whereas the other team were put together last minute in “hot seats” with an uncooperative Product Owner (with hidden agenda, poor leadership and ownership).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also randomly invited 4 interns to play special behavior variants to bring either a positive or negative energy in both teams to observe how energy could impact the team’s ability to self-organise &amp;amp; self-manage. The rest of the members were invited as observers to notice how ownership emerges in each team in getting things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What we have learned in running the game&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unexpected challenges to get volunteers taking PO roles - Perhaps because we underestimated stigma, uncertainty and perceived accountability of the role play
“Sticky situation” between the urge to taking shortcuts to move on from impasse situation (by arrowing PO) and holding the space for learning process to emerge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Huge relief when members stepped up and volunteer to hold on to the “cactus” (be it as PO or Presenters) - In hindsight, this is probably the best outcome because those volunteers will have both motivation and legitimacy as leader as compared if we are to appoint them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Both teams prevail and manage to deliver their pitch despite obstacles. There’s no lack of creativity and improvisations -  including last minute presentations being created! Most heartwarming is to see how the rest of the members are cheering and rallying behind them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As shared by observers - challenging situations provides opportunity for leadership to naturally emerge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Even with our invitation sharing, only 1 member has clear awareness that they can say no, others are trying to make things done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stages-of-team-development-to-unite-and-create-success-together&quot;&gt;Stages of Team Development to unite and create success together&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving from how individuals can solicit and embrace ownership, we looked into how groups of people can self-organise as a team. We became aware of the tension between taking ownership, providing autonomy (freedom to act independently of others), ensuring alignment (pushing towards the same goal) and upholding accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/08/ptl7-3.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Team Development&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;A model that resonated with us is &lt;em&gt;“The Drexler-Sibbet Team Performance Model”&lt;/em&gt; which describes “predictable progression of concerns that will help us understand how people come to work together as a team and eventually achieve increasing levels of performance”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This model helped us reflect where we are in the process to identify gaps that hindered our progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What worked well&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Create common ground”&lt;/strong&gt;: Our team was formed almost by circumstance rather than by choice. However, all of us took that “leap of faith” when we realised that we shared pain points that we are all motivated to solve. We also strengthened our common ground by identifying what we are bringing to the team and creating an accepting environment for sharing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Take the time to build trust”&lt;/strong&gt;: We felt a mutual regard with each other when we put effort into preparing for meetings, reflecting deeply on THE WHY of this topic, and giving each other feedback. At the same time, there are times when we are cautious as we may not personally feel confident enough with others to drive specific ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Align and Focus”&lt;/strong&gt;: The topic is HUGE. With so much research possibilities, we felt disoriented due to lack of focus. However, by clarifying our shared  assumptions and expectations, we refined our goals on the topic of  “ownership” which strengthened our team alignment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What didn’t work so well&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Given our early start (in May), we became complacent of time - took for granted the time to perform autonomous / independent research work (e.g. reading up materials, exploring possible avenues about the topic) without clearly assigning roles, goals &amp;amp; commitments. We underestimated how fast time passes and found ourselves fast-forwarded to D-3 weeks!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Unbounded Autonomy”&lt;/strong&gt;: Deadline has suddenly become a constraint to work autonomously as well as an ally in realigning our actions. We switchded gears from once-in-a-while meetings to daily meetups :) In hindsight, we might have lowered our “stress” by having shorter, more regular alignment sessions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Absence of Strategy”&lt;/strong&gt;: We found it disorienting without strategy as we didn’t have a reference model for what to do &amp;amp; how we should self-organise. These challenges helped us realise how we can use The Performance Model to see where we were stuck, evaluate, and resolve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What actions we made for team growth&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Show up”&lt;/strong&gt;: With the deadline looming, we created working agreements to commit daily evening updates and keep each other accountable. It was quite an effort, but all of these interactions, commitments help us appreciate each others’ sincerity, reliability, competence and charge our “trust battery”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Build on one another - make progress together”&lt;/strong&gt;: There are many different ideas that we initially attempted to explore - but eventually it boils down to how they fit the constraints of run sheets. We stopped creating individual note boards and started making actual meetup placeholders / slides. We also agreed on daily tasks to accomplish by next day’s meeting and build upon each other’s work. Doing so helped us move from “individual ownership” (i.e. your work vs my work) into “group ownership” (i.e. our work)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Rest to Persevere”&lt;/strong&gt;: We experienced a high sense of progress before being “brought down to reality” when we had the test run at D-7: significantly increasing anxiety, frustration, and tension. Recognising that burning the midnight oil has taken a toll on our personal energy, we collectively decided to take a much needed weekend break. By choosing to rest &amp;amp; stopping “maximising efficiency”, prioritising connection and finding back our clarity that we all want to deliver “fun” and meaningful meetup helps us reset and bounce back.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;members-ahas&quot;&gt;Members’ AHAs:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ownership takes courage - i.e. to take the leap of faith, to trust and to hold a space for others to step up and flourish. It was encouraging and heartwarming when that moment happened.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trust yourself, trust your members, trust your audience. They will bring you more than you ever expect. Even if things didn’t go the direction we planned, or are not in your comfort zone, it is still worth it to jump in and give it a try. It might be related to real life when evolving and building a team, related to our “invitation” as well - The best lesson is always about self-discovering, creating stories together but not storying-listening.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t underestimate how fast time flies. Don’t overestimate how much 1 motivated individual can do – a chain is only as strong as its weakest link.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;side-quest&quot;&gt;Side Quest&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inviting Leadership&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;The Culture Game&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Describes how good invitation should be formed and how invitation relates to leadership, authority, and boundary. We could not get to read the actual book, so we read snippets of it in the following &lt;a href=&quot;https://res.infoq.com/articles/book-review-inviting-leadership/en/resources/The%20Guide%20to%20Inviting%20Leadership-1556704567943.pdf&quot;&gt;links&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/pierre-yves-hittelet/navy-seal-leadership-lessons.html&quot;&gt;Extreme Ownership&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This book prescribes that “the best leaders don’t just take responsibility for their job. They take extreme ownership of everything that impacts their mission. All responsibility for success and failure rests with the leader. Whether a team succeeds or fails is all up to the leader. The leader’s attitude sets the tone for the entire team”. It highlights roles and responsibilities for leaders to first demonstrate ownership before expecting ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.leadershipnow.com/leadingblog/2020/09/leadership_is_language.html&quot;&gt;Leadership is Language&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Along the line Inviting Leadership, this book highlighted how choosing the right words can dramatically improve commitment, decision-making and execution on a team. I particularly found the proposed playbook insightful. One example related to ownership: If you want to keep your commitments, don’t make it about the behavior but more about who you are. Not, “I can’t,” but rather, “I don’t.” A way to execute this play is to focus on learning by “developing hypotheses to test rather than making decisions to execute.” Rather than “What are we going to do?” create a mindset of “What are we going to learn?”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://homepages.se.edu/cvonbergen/files/2018/02/Leaders-Eat-Last.pdf&quot;&gt;Leaders eat last&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;“Cactus Role” is a relevant analogy for embracing ownership and leadership since it is indeed challenging - This book gives me a good reminder that “Leadership is not a license to do less; it is a responsibility to do more… The effects are not always easily measured and they are not always immediate. Leadership is always a commitment to human beings… Leaders eat last”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Albert Hardy</name></author><category term="workshop" /><summary type="html">“How might we build a sense of ownership to create success together?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PTL #6 - Mentorship</title><link href="tanutama.com/notes/2021/08/ptl-meetup6/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PTL #6 - Mentorship" /><published>2021-08-03T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-08-03T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>tanutama.com/notes/2021/08/ptl-meetup6</id><content type="html" xml:base="tanutama.com/notes/2021/08/ptl-meetup6/">&lt;p class=&quot;sublead&quot;&gt;“How might we learn to be a great mentor?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/08/ptl6-1b.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Meetup Circle&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;!-- Facilitated by Hazel, Gia, Cherps --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we learnt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;💭What mentoring is&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;🛠 Understand the Principles of Meaningful Mentoring&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;🔍Discover what you can offer as a mentor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-mentoring&quot;&gt;What is Mentoring?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mentoring is learning relationship - The primary purpose is to drive personal growth; building skills, knowledge and understanding.  While mentors may use coaching skills, their role is usually wider beyond learning specific competencies or tasks. Mentors may offer resources, advice, experiences, knowledge and opinions to nurture the development of a less experienced mentee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your coach is like a mirror&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Asking powerful questions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helping you discover potential you didn’t know you had inside you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your mentor is like a partner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Walking together with you, on a similar path&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helping you with knowledge and perspectives that may be new to you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-type-of-mentor-can-i-be&quot;&gt;What type of mentor can I be?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Career mentor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guide mentees on career goals and help them work through career transitions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Usually seniors in a similar industry and/or discipline&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peer mentor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Offer on-the-job training for new employees&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Help mentees settle into a new role, to learn new skills, processes and practices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Life mentor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use one’s past experience to encourage and support their mentees for their careers and/or personal growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aren’t always professional coaches or teachers– could be a family member, friend, or colleague&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you’re someone who’s just starting out, you can still share your knowledge and experiences with someone else!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;personal-journey-map&quot;&gt;Personal Journey Map&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tool to help you discover what you can offer as a mentor.&lt;br /&gt;
Some reflections you can use when preparing the journey map:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What has my life been so far?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the turning points that have shaped or shifted me?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What have I been through that I have empathy and authority to speak about?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What value can I bring to other people and teams?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mentoring-conversation-and-roles&quot;&gt;Mentoring Conversation and Roles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/08/ptl6-2.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Arc of Coaching&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;Mentor wears different hats to help the mentee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coach&lt;/strong&gt; : Mentors will ask probing questions, provide honest and direct feedback, and give insights into the mind of the mentee.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Devil’s advocate&lt;/strong&gt; : Mentors will challenge the mentee and get them out of their comfort zone. That means playing the opposite side, and have the mentee learn to  be ok with discomfort.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Support System&lt;/strong&gt; : Mentors a huge fans of the mentees. They celebrate the big and small wins, show support when mentees face setbacks, and consistently provide encouragement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resource&lt;/strong&gt; : Mentors have countless resources from tools to people to jobs. The mentor is inclined to provide the relevant tools &amp;amp; learning lessons, introduce their network &amp;amp; connections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;principles-of-meaningful-mentoring---how-can-i-be-a-better-mentor&quot;&gt;Principles of Meaningful Mentoring - How can I be a better mentor?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hand out fishing rods, not fish&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
This means to get the mentee to find the answer, not dole out advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delay giving advice. Get mentee &amp;amp; reflect more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Share anecdotes, broad principles, of different solutions. Get mentee to tell you how it applies their context and how they’d like to tailor it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encourage emotions to be explored&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
To really address challenges and begin to grow, it’s key to recognise the feelings that emerge are valid, and explore them if permission is given.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Give space to acknowledge the difficult emotions. Mentor to share their past failures, Mentee to share their difficult emotions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take the time to understand each others career paths, goals, hopes, fears, and lifestyle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Help the mentee step back and see the bigger why&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Check far blind spots &amp;amp; help them see through others perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Play out scenarios to practice difficult conversations: “How might other stakeholders feel about or view your idea?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go back to the beginning, such the purpose behind problem or situation. “Why are you here? Why does your company exist?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep the mentoring relationship mutually benefitting&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Keeping both parties energized about the relationship depends on mutual learning. Make sure mentors are benefiting too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mentors are proactive in seeing the opportunity to learn from their mentees &amp;amp; glean what’s relevant to their own work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mentors intuition in dealing with situations: Their own relationships their boss &amp;amp; reports; Industry trends and intelligence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mentees to ask mentors what they can contribute to them: “What excites you about I’m working on?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledge and celebrate small wins&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This builds your mentee’s confidence and keep them motivated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Show love and appreciation for mentee’s attempts, success or fail.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In work setting, mentor can publicly recognise the mentee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/08/ptl6-1.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Group Photo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;h3 id=&quot;side-quest&quot;&gt;Side Quest:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1NUdqvFMjyOLmL4ORjMxgw4H28n8iA8Qp/view&quot;&gt;Practice telling your public story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.togetherplatform.com/blog/what-is-the-purpose-of-mentoring&quot;&gt;Benefits to being a mentor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://matterapp.com/blog/mentor-and-mentee-roles-responsibilities-and-relationships&quot;&gt;Mentor and mentee roles, responsibilities and relationships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://review.firstround.com/we-studied-100-mentor-mentee-matches-heres-what-makes-mentorship-work&quot;&gt;What makes mentorship work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://review.firstround.com/how-to-be-a-career-changing-mentor-25-tips-from-the-best-mentors-we-know&quot;&gt;How to be a career changing mentor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Albert Hardy</name></author><category term="workshop" /><summary type="html">“How might we learn to be a great mentor?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PTL #5 - Resilience</title><link href="tanutama.com/notes/2021/07/ptl-meetup5/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PTL #5 - Resilience" /><published>2021-07-20T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-07-20T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>tanutama.com/notes/2021/07/ptl-meetup5</id><content type="html" xml:base="tanutama.com/notes/2021/07/ptl-meetup5/">&lt;p class=&quot;sublead&quot;&gt;“How might we build resilient product leaders?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/07/ptl5-1.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Meetup Circle&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;Facilitated by Ridzwan, Jocelyn, Lin Chou&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we learnt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What does resilience mean to each one of us&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Appreciate that resilience sits on a sliding scale and is adaptive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What we can do to strengthen our individual and team resilience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Impact of mindset on the resilience of your team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-resilience&quot;&gt;What is resilience?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/07/ptl5-2.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;What is Resilience&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;Psychologists define resilience as the process of adapting well in the face of adversity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resilience = being tough?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
People tend to associate resilience with toughness, as if a strong-willed person who always bouncing back after challenges. &lt;em&gt;“Resilience is like having the life force of a cockroach and resistance to defeat”&lt;/em&gt; .&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resilience = Grit/ Perseverance?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In Product, nothing is definite. Consistency of pursue isn’t a positive trait. &lt;em&gt;“Having grit is amiable but I could be making the same mistake again…People who were right a lot of time were people who often change their minds”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-types-of-resilient&quot;&gt;3 Types of Resilient:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Natural Resilience&lt;/strong&gt; : It is a gift that we forgotten after the age seven. But, we can relearn it again as it is always inside us.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adaptive Resilience&lt;/strong&gt; : It is a transformative experience on learning and growing after each setback than repeating the same mistake. The ‘trial by fire.’ This occurs when challenging circumstances force you to learn and change and adapt. Learning how to roll with life’s punches can help you build resilience and grow stronger as a result. (intelligent for product person: pivoting &amp;amp; continuous learning).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Restored Resilience&lt;/strong&gt; : To heal from past, present and future traumas in a healthier way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reference: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.act-resilient.org/Site/Blog/Entries/2012/8/28_The_Three_Types_of_Resilience.html&quot;&gt;act-resilient&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;resilient-strategies-to-self-care&quot;&gt;Resilient strategies to self-care&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/07/ptl5-3.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Resilience can be improved&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/07/ptl5-4.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Connection&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/07/ptl5-5.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Clarity&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;Resilience is a response to adversity. It is both measurable and trainable. It is not fixed; but can be learned, taught, practiced, and developed. 
How we think about ourselves has an impact in our capacity being resilient. You can grow your resilience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humans are hardwired to react to the bad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your skill at managing negativity determines your resilience.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How you define yourself matters a great deal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abstract thinking may increase resilience.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go sweat the small stuff. (Pay attention to yourself)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reference: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/tech-support/201503/5-things-you-need-know-about-resilience&quot;&gt;5 Things You Need to Know About Resilience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7 Resilient strategies to self-care after setback, fatigue, and burnout.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exercise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make time for solitude.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engage in positive self-talk.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get out more and experience life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn from failure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cultivate both humor and curiosity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have realistic expectations for yourself and others (your client, boss, team, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reference:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.gale.com/apps/doc/A233501749/AONE?u=anon~9913bb59&amp;amp;sid=googleScholar&amp;amp;xid=507553a9&quot;&gt;“Resiliency counseling in economic hard times.”&lt;/a&gt; by Javors, Irene Rosenberg&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;resilient-teams---hmw-increase-the-resilience-of-our-teams&quot;&gt;Resilient teams - HMW increase the resilience of our teams?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why should we care about team resilience?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only 2% of teams are resilient. Can be identified by specific behaviors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Translates into
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Better team performance&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Achieve business results&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;People reaching their potential at work&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resilience isn’t just a matter of “toughing it out.” It is a mental state to feel comfortable when being uncomfortable.&lt;br /&gt;
Bearing up under pressure and in stressful situations is certainly part of being resilient, but it’s just one part. It’s often their ability to mentally handle the intangibles (weather, unknown obstacles, attitude about ability, illness, a nagging injury, being cold and wet 24/7, and the fear of failure) that carries the few that make it across the finish line.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resilient leaders beget resilient teams:  It starts with you as a leader. You can’t build resilient teams without first being resilient yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Teams are a highly effective lever for increasing resilience. You can increase individual resilience with 1-to-1 coaching. What you say matters…the way you say it matters!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/07/ptl5-6.jpg&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;What you say matters&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3 Practices to Build Your Leadership Resilience.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/07/ptl5-7.png&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Practices&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal Energy Management&lt;/strong&gt; : Manage your own resistance. “Show up,” give your best, and relinquish attachment to the outcome. Stay in the present.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shift Your Lenses&lt;/strong&gt; : Take charge of how you think about adversity. Understand your beliefs about the situation, and choose your response. Exercise compassion for yourself and others.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sense of Purpose&lt;/strong&gt; : Develop a “personal why” that gives your life meaning. This helps you better face setbacks and challenges. Also, look for ways that crisis and adversity may connect to your larger life purpose. Lessons can be gleaned from hardships.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reference:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ccl.org/articles/leading-effectively-articles/leadership-resiliency-handling-stress-uncertainty-and-setbacks/&quot;&gt;“Leadership Resilience: Handling Stress, Uncertainty, and Setbacks.”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;takeaways&quot;&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stress and challenges will not go away, but our capacity to mitigate their impact can grow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resilient people don’t deny their human responses to loss and pain. The more we feel all of our feelings, the more resilient we are.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having a larger community base and support system builds resilience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;side-quest&quot;&gt;Side Quest&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2019/03/12/amazon-billionaire-jeff-bezos-explains-why-the-smartest-people-change-their-minds-often.html&quot;&gt;Why the smartest people change their minds often&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.glassdoor.com/employers/blog/only-2-of-teams-are-resilient-heres-how-to-change-that/&quot;&gt;Only 2 of teams are resilient&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rework.withgoogle.com/blog/five-keys-to-a-successful-google-team/&quot;&gt;5-keys to a successful google team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.betterup.com/blog/the-key-to-a-more-resilient-organization-is-more-resilient-teams&quot;&gt;The key to a more resilient organization is more resilient teams&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mindfulbydesign.com/fixed-vs-growth-two-ends-mindset-continuum/&quot;&gt;Fixed vs growth: two ends mindset continuum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/brentgleeson/2021/04/13/resilience-in-leadership-how-to-lead-and-win-despite-change-and-obstacles/&quot;&gt;Resilience in leadership&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2020/09/what-really-makes-us-resilient?ab=hero-main-text&quot;&gt;What really makes us resilient?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Albert Hardy</name></author><category term="workshop" /><summary type="html">“How might we build resilient product leaders?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PTL #4 - Sustainability</title><link href="tanutama.com/notes/2021/07/ptl-meetup4/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PTL #4 - Sustainability" /><published>2021-07-10T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-07-10T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>tanutama.com/notes/2021/07/ptl-meetup4</id><content type="html" xml:base="tanutama.com/notes/2021/07/ptl-meetup4/">&lt;p class=&quot;sublead&quot;&gt;“How might we build more ethical and  sustainable products?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/07/ptl4-0.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   height=&quot;480px&quot;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;PTL #4&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;!-- Facilitated by Azri and Adhitya --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we learnt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;understand the larger responsibility that we and the organisation have&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how all of us are a part of an interconnected system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how might we find the sustainable sweet spot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unintended-consequences&quot;&gt;Unintended consequences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good intentions can result in far bigger problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/07/ptl4-1.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   height=&quot;200px&quot;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Unintended consequences&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interconnected-systems&quot;&gt;Interconnected Systems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our current economic system often incentivizes waste generation and encourages producers to manipulate their products to be used up and then discarded for something new in increasingly shorter cycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As product people, it’s our job to ensure that our products are kind — i.e. they are ethical and do not cause any harm. An ethical product is an offering that does not cause any harm, neither to its users nor the planet. The former includes negatively impacting the people’s mental wellbeing. The latter comprises contributing to climate change by developing and providing the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do so, one needs to consider potential unintended consequences to 3 main parts of an interconnected systems: planet, product, and/or people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- https://stackoverflow.com/questions/29053280/jekyll-markup-appearing-in-p-tag --&gt;
&lt;!-- include image-full.html file=&quot;cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;demo caption&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot;  --&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/2021/07/ptl4-2.JPG&quot;  alt=&quot;Topic&quot;   height=&quot;480px&quot;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Interconnected System&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

    

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social systems are the intangible social scaffolding that humans have developed over time to function as a society.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Industrial systems involve most of goods and services that fill our lives.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ecosystems are all the natural services that keep the Earth alive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-might-we-create-a-more-ethical-product&quot;&gt;How might we create a more ethical product?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some questions to reflect on&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is our intention?&lt;br /&gt;
  Are we truly creating products that will enrich the people’s lives?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have we considered their mental wellbeing?&lt;br /&gt;
  Should we notify our users for every interactions that happened? What is the threshold between being  useful and stress-inducing? Should we show content that receives high viewing even though it might promote violence or hatred?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is our business model ethical?&lt;br /&gt;
  Should we charge our users or provide them for free? who will bear the cost? Products are value-creating vehicles: They exist to generate benefits for the users and business. When digital products are offered for free, monetisation typically takes place in form of exposing users to ads and selling their data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How are our design and technology choices affecting people, industry, and the planet?&lt;br /&gt;
  Did we create an experience that misleads and pushes users in a direction that benefits the interests of the company rather than the user?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s the environmental impact of our product?
  It is important that we raise public awareness so that, collectively, we can implement meaningful personal and systemic changes to reduce the environmental impact and successfully transition to a low-carbon economy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;takeaways&quot;&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While there are values in getting things a lot faster - are we actually designing product that are good for humanity?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Good” is a spectrum and not binary. What is good for you is ‘subjective’, i.e. What may be good for you may have negative repercussions to other people.&lt;br /&gt;
How do you define something is good for the planet? Where do you draw the line?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your intention matters. How do you perceived the problem? How are you going to remedy the unintended consequences?
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Necessity and excessive&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sustainability vs. minimalism - Is “minimalism” a better approach when creating a product?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Time” should be one variable to consider
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Is a product good for short-term? Long-term?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Should we build a product that last long and benefit more people?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Should we build a product that has its own “expiration date” ?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What do we sacrifice when pursuing sustainability?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Good” isn’t just a state (you can’t just say that you are a good or a bad company), it should be a direction.&lt;br /&gt;
 As product people, it’s unavoidable for us to make some short-term decisions that do harm intentionally or unintentionally BUT the sum total of our decisions and our product should benefit the three Ps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask the tough questions; Recognise the tension - Be deliberate and intentional in making the design choice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The path to be more sustainable is a complex domain and should be treated as such. Not for the reason to discourage us from taking any actions, more to illustrate that there are many moving parts to this picture. We might discover more questions and that can feel overwhelming… What’s more important is to be able to hold the space to ask these questions; as an individual, a family member, a friend, a colleague, or a leader in our own organisation. And move towards actions that we believe in, measure them, and continue from there.”&lt;/em&gt; -  cited from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/posts/azrirashid_producttoniclab-activity-6822382008396861440-xrfp&quot;&gt;Azri&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;side-quest&quot;&gt;Side Quest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/disruptive-design/a-guide-to-life-cycle-thinking-b762ab49bce3&quot;&gt;Life Cycle Thinking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/disruptive-design/quick-guide-to-sustainable-design-strategies-641765a86fb8&quot;&gt;Quick guide to sustainable design strategies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.romanpichler.com/blog/product-ethics&quot;&gt;Think about Product Ethics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/product-hospice/a-code-of-ethics-for-product-managers-8488b7c1914f&quot;&gt;Code of ethics for product managers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BiSYoeqb_VY&quot;&gt;Example product design life cycle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.mit.edu/2021/how-to-reduce-environmental-impact-next-virtual-meeting-0304&quot;&gt;How to reduce the environmental impact of your next virtual meeting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Albert Hardy</name></author><category term="workshop" /><summary type="html">“How might we build more ethical and sustainable products?”</summary></entry></feed>